Philip J. Klass Collection 1948-2000 Mss.Ms.Coll.59
American Philosophical Society
Philip J. Klass Collection
1948-2000
Mss.Ms.Coll.59
American Philosophical Society
36.0 Linear feet
An electrical engineer and senior editor for Aviation Week and Space Technology, Philip Klass began investigating UFOs in 1966 after participating in a panel discussion on the subject for the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE). From that time forward Klass has investigated UFO sightings in an effort to find a credible prosaic explanation, and became one of the most widely recognized UFO "debunkers." A founding member of the Committee for the Scientific Investigation of Claims of the Paranormal (CSICOP), serving on the Executive Council and the UFO subcommittee, Klass has authored seven books and numerous articles on UFOs, including the Skeptics UFO Newsletter in 1989. In the early 1970s, he became interested in space based weapons, and began collecting material related to the Strategic Defense Initiative (SDI) for a possible book. The Klass Collection relate to his forty-plus years of investigating UFO sightings, and includes correspondence with many of the leading UFOlogists, both pro and con. The collection contains case files, subject files, and correspondence. In addition, Klass' SDI material is included.
Klass, Philip J.
Separated Materials note
The following books have been transferred to the Printed Materials Department for storage. Please consult the Curator of Books for access.
Ackerman, John. To Catch a Flying Saucer: A Scientific Theory of UFO's. San Diego, CA: Univelt, Inc., 1989.
Adams, Russell B., Jr. ed. Mysteries of the Unknown: The UFO Phenomenon. Alexandria, VA: Time-Life Books, 1987.
Banchs, Roberto E. Fenomenos aereos Inusuales: Un enfoque biopsicosocial. Buenos Aires: LEUKA, 1994.
Basterfield, Keith. UFOs: The Image Hypothesis: Close Encounters of an Australian Kind. Sydney, New South Wales: Reed, 1981. Call No.: 629.4 B29c.
Beam Defense: An Alternative to Nuclear Destruction. Fallbrook, CA: Aero Publishers, Inc., 1983.
Billig, Otto. Flying Saucers: magic in the Skies. Cambridge, MA.: Schenkman Pub. Co., 1982. Call No.: 629.4 B49f.
Blania-Bolnar, Zbigniew. Zdarzenie W Emilcinie. Pandora, 1995.
Blum, Howard. Out There: The Government's Secret Quest for Extraterrestrials. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1990. Call No.: 629.4 B627o.
Boyd, Robert D. International Who's Who in UFOlogy Directory. Mobile, AL: Southeastern Press, 1988.
Brookesmith, Peter. Alien Abductions. London: Blandford, 1998.
Brookesmith, Peter. UFO: The Government Files. New York: Barnes & Noble, 1996.
Brown, Courtney. Cosmic Voyage: A Scientific Discovery of Extraterrestrials Visiting Earth. New York: Dutton, 1996.
Butler, Brenda, et. al. Sky Crash: a Cosmic Conspiracy. Suffolk: N. Spearman, 1984. Call No.: 629.4 B97s.
Carter, Aston B. and David N. Schwarts, ed. Ballistic Missile Defense. Washington D.C.: The Brookings Institution, 1984.
Center for UFO Studies. Associate Newsletter / Center for UFO Studies. Lima, Ohio: The Center, Physical Description. Call No.: 629.4 C33an.
Chayes, Antonia J. and Paul Doty, ed. Defending Deterrence: Managing the ABM Treaty Regime into the 21st Century. Washington, D.C.: Pegamon-Brassey's, 1989. Call No.:
Cohen, Daniel. The World of UFOs. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1978. Call No.: 629.4 C66w.
Coleman, William. I Was a Project Blue Book Consultant. Tokyo: Green Arrow Books, 1990. Call No.: 629.4 C67I.
Collins, John M. Military Space Forces: The Next 50 Years. Washington, D.C.: Pegamon-Brassey's, 1989.
Condon, Edward U. Final Report of the Scientific Study of Unidentified Flying Objects. Boulder, CO: University of Colorado, 1968. Call No.: 629.4 C75s.
Conroy, Ed. Report on Communion: an Independent Investigation of and Commentary on Whitley Strieber's Communion. New York: Morrow, 1989. Call No.: 629.4 C76r.
Cousineau, Phil. UFO: Secrets Revealed. New York: Harper Collins, 1995.
Cousineau, Phil. UFOs: A Manual for the Millennium. New York: Harper Collins, 1995.
David, Jay, ed. Flying Saucers Have Arrived! New York: World Pub. Co., 1970. Call No.: 629.4 D28f.
Downing, Barry H. The Bible and Flying Saucers. N.Y.: Avon Books, 1970. Call No.: 629.4 D75b.
Dykes, Mervyn. Strangers in Our Skies: UFOs over New Zealand. Lower Hutt, New Zealand: INL Print, 1981. Call No.: 629.4 D99s.
Edwards, Frank. Flying Saucers, Here and Now! New York: L. Stuart, 1967. Call No.: 629.4 Ed9f.
Fawcett, George D. Quarter Century Studies of UFOs in Florida, North Carolina and Tennessee. Mount Airy, N.C.: Pioneer Printing Co., 1975. Call No.: 629.4 F28q.
Fawcett, Lawrence and Barry J. Greenwood. Clear Intent: The Government Coverup of the UFO Exerience. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1984.
Flying saucer material-various paper backs. Table of contents available. Call No.: 629.4 F67b.
Flying saucer material-various periodicals. Table of contents available. Call No.: 629.4 F67p.
Fogarty, Quentin. Let's Hope They're Friendly! Wellington, Australia: Reed, 1982. Call No.: 629.4 F68L.
Fowler, Raymond E. The Anderson Affair: Phase Two. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall, 1982.
Frazier, Kendrick, et. al. ed. The UFO Invasion: The Roswell Incident, Alien Abductions, and Government Coverups. Amherst, NY: Prometheus Books, 1997.
Friedman, Stanton T. and Don Berliner. Crash at Corona: The Definitive Study of the Roswell Incident. New York: Marlowe & Co., 1995.
Friesner, Esther M. and Martin H. Greenberg. Alien Pregnant by Elvis. New York: DAW Books, 1994.
Fuller, John G. The Interrupted Journey: Two lost Hours "Aboard a Flying Saucer" New York: Dial Press, 1966. Call No.: 629.4 F95I.
Gadd, Laurence, comp. The Second Book of the Strange. New York: Prometheus Books, 1981. Call No.: 629.4 G12s.
Gantois, Door J. M. UFO's en Andere Vreemde Natuurverschijnselen. Zutphen: Thieme, n.d. Call No.: 629.4 G15u.
Goldsmith, Donald, and Tobias Owen. The Search for Life in the Universe. Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley Publishing, 1992.
Haines, Ricard F. ed. UFO Phenomena and the Behavioral Scientist. Metuchen, N.J.: The Scarecrow Press, 1979.
Hobana, Ion and Julien Weverbergh. UFO's from Behind the Iron Curtain New York: Bantam Books, 1975. Call No.: 629.4 H65u.
Hopkins, Budd. Intruders: The Incredible Visitations at Copley Woods. New York: Random House, 1987.
Hopkins, Budd. Missing Time. New York: Ballatine Books, 1981.
Hopkins, Budd. Missing Time: a Documented Study of UFO Abductions. New York: R. Marek Publishers, 1981. Call No.: 629.4 H77m.
Hynek, J. Allen, and Jacques Vallee. The Edge of Reality: A Progress report on Unidentified Flying Objects. Chicago, Il.: Henry Regnery Co., 1975.
Jansma, Sidney J., Sr. UFO's and Evolution. ??:??, 1981.
Journal of UFO Studies. Volume 2, 1990. 629.4 J82
Jung, C. G. Flying Saucers; a Modern Myth of Things Seen in the Skies. Translated from the German by R. F. C. Hull. New York: New American Library, 1969. Call No.: 629.4 J95f.
Kampen, Hans van. Ufo's boven de Lage Landen: een uitgebreid overzicht met opzienbarende onthullingen. Bussum: Kern, 1978. Call No.: 629.4 K12u.
Karas, Thomas. The New High Ground: Strategies and Weapons of Space-Age War. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1983.
Keyhoe, Donald E. and Gordon I. R. Lore, Jr. ed. UFOs: a New Look; a Special Report. Washington: National Investigations Committee on Aerial Phenomena, 1969. Call No.: 629.4 Pam. no.21.
Kinder, Gary. Light Years: an Investigation into the Extraterrestrial Experiences of Eduard Meier. New York: Atlantic Monthly Press, 1987. Call No.: 629.4 K575L.
Knight, David C. UFOs, a Pictorial History from Antiquity to the Present. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1979. Call No.: 629.4 K74u.
Krapf, Phililp H. The Contact has Begun: The True Story of a Journalist's Enounter with Alien Beings. Carlsbad, CA: Hay House, 1998.
Krapf, Phillip H. The Challenge of Contact: A Mainstream Journalist's Report on Interplanetary Diplomacy. Novato, CA: Origin Press, 2001.
Lore, Jr. Gordon I. R., and Harold H. Deneault, Jr. Mysteries of the Skies; UFOs in Perspective. Englewood Cliffs, N.J., Prentice-Hall 1968. Call No.: 629.4 L89m.
Lorenzen, Coral E. Flying Saucers: the Startling Evidence of the Invasion from Outer Space. New York: Signet Book, Published by the New American Library, 1966. Call No.: 629.4 L88f.r.
Lorenzen, Coral E. UFOs: The Whole Story. New York: New American Library, 1969. Call No.: 629.4 L88uf.
Lorenzen, Coral E. Flying Saucer Occupants. New York: New American Library, 1967. Call No.: 629.4 L88fL.
Lorenzen, Jim. UFO's Over the Americas. New York: New American Library, 1968. Call No.: 629.4 L88u.
Mack, John E. Abductions: Human Encounters with Aliens.. Accord, MA: Wheeler Pub., 1994. Call No.: 629.4 M25a
Magosci, Oscar. My Space Odyssey in UFOs. Toronto: Quest Group, 1980. Call No.: 629.4 M27m.
Mathes, J. H. and Lenora Huett. The Amnesia Factor: Extraterrestrial Communications Breakthrough. Millbrae, CA: Celestial Arts, 1975. Call No.: 629.4 M42a.
Matheson, Terry. Alien Abductions: Creating a Modern Phenomenon. Amherst, NY: Prometheus Books, 1998.
Mayer, Ann Margaret. Who's Out There?: UFO Encounters. New York: J. Messner, 1979. Call No.: 629.4 M45w.
McCampbell, James M. UFOlogy. Millbrae, CA: Celestial Arts, 1976. Call No.: 629.4 M13u.
McHugh, Tom. Flying Saucers are Everywhere. Amherst, NY: Prometheus Books, 1995.
Meaden, George Terence. The Circles Effect and Its Mysteries. Bradford-on-Avon, Wiltshire, U.K.: Artetech Publishing Col., 1989.
Milton, A. Fenner, et. al. Making Space Defense Work: Must the Superpowers Cooperate? Washington, D.C.: Pergamon-Brassey's, 1989.
MUFON UFO Symposium Proceedings. 1975, 1977-1982, 1985-1989. Call No.: 629.4 M98s
Nakamura, Shozo. The Space Aliens Exist. Tokyo: Green Arrow Books, n.d. Call No.: 629.4 N15s.
National Aeronautics and Space Administration. Field Resonance Propulsion Concept. Houston: Lyndon B. Johnson Space Center, 1979. Call No.: 629.4 Pam. no.22.
Nesheim, Eric and Leif Nesheim. Saucer Attack!: Pop Culture in the Golden Age of Flying Saucers. Los Angeles, CA: Kitchen Sink Press, 1997.
Oberg, James E. UFOs & Outer Space Mysteries: A Sympathetic Skeptic's Report. Norfolk, VA: Donning, 1982.
Olsen, Thomas M.. The Reference for Outstanding UFO Sighting Reports: UFOIRC-6601, November 1966 Riderwood, Md.: UFO Information Retrieval Center, 1966. Call No.: 629.4 OL8r.
Pacheco, Nelson S. and Tommy R. Blann. Unmasking the Enemy: Visions Around the World and Global Deception in the End Times. Arlington, VA: Bendan Press, 1993.
Pawlicki, T.B. How to Build a Flying Saucer: and Other Proposals in Speculative Eengineerings. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, 1981. Call No.: 629.4 P28h.
Pinkney, John. Alien Honeycomb: the First Solid Evidence of UFOs. Sydney: Pan Books, 1980. Call No.: 629.4 P65a.
Pope, Nick. Open Skies, Closed Minds: For the First Time a Government UFO Expert Speaks Out. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1996.
Pope, Nick. The Uninvited: An Expose of the Alien Abduction Phenomenon. London: Simon & Schuster, 1997.
Randle, Kevin D. A History of UFO Crashes. New York: Avon Books, 1995. Call No.: 629.4 R14h
Randle, Kevin D. Scientific UFOlogy: Roswell and beyond-how Scientific Ufology Can Prove the Reality of UFO's. New York: HarperCollins, 1999. Call No.: 629.4 R14s
Randle, Kevin D. The October Scenario: UFO Abductions, Theories about them and a Prediction of When they will Return. Iowa City: Middle Coast Publishing, 1988.
Randle, Kevin D. The UFO Case Book. New York: Warner Books, 1989. Call No.: 629.4 R14u
Randle, Kevin D. and Donald R. Schmitt. The Truth about the UFO Crash at Roswell. New York: Avon Books, 1994.
Randles, Jenny. Abduction. London: Guild Publishing, 1988.
Randles, Jenny. Alien Contacts & Abductions: The Real Story from the Other Side. New York: Sterling Publishing, 1994.
Rasmussen, Richard Michael. The UFO Literature: a Comprehensive Annotated Bibliography of Works in English. Jefferson, N.C.: McFarland, 1985. Call No.: 016.6294 R19u.
Reeves-Stevens, Garfield. Nighteyes. New York: Bantam Books, 1989.
Rhea, John. SDI: What Could Happen. Harrisburg, PA: Stackpole Books, 1988.
Sanderson, Ivan Terence. Uninvited Visitors; a Biologist looks at UFO's. New York: Cowles Education Corp., 1967. Call No.: 629.4 Sa5u.
Seller, Charles E. UFO. Chicago, IL: Contemporary Books, 1997.
Sheaffer, Robert. The UFO Verdict: Examining the Evidence. Buffalo, N.Y.: Prometheus Books, 1981.
Sifakis, Carl. Official Guide to UFO Sightings. New York: Sterling Pub., 1979. Call No.: 629.4 Si2o.
Skeptic. Volume 7, Number 4, 1999. Call No.: 629.4 Sk2
Spencer, John W. No Earthly Explanation: Mankind: A Space Experiment. Springfield, MA.: Phillips Publishing Co., 1974. Call No.: 629.4 Sp3n.
Spielberg, Steven. Close Encounters of the Third Kind: a Novel. New York: Dell Publisheing Co., 1977. Call No.: 629.4 Sp4c.
Stanford, Ray. Socorro "Saucer" in a Pentagon Pantry. Austin, TX: Blueapple Books, 1976. Call No.: 629.4 St2s.
Startup, Bill. The Kaikoura UFOs. Aukland, N.Z.: Hodder and Stoughton, 1980.
Steiger, Brad. Flying Saucers are Hostile. New York: Award Books, 1967. Call No.: 629.4 St3f.
Steiger, Brad. Flying Saucer Invasion: Target-Earth. New York: Award Books, 1969. Call No.: 629.4 St3fL.
Stevens, Wendelle C., and. Paul Dong. UFOS Over Modern China; a Survey of the Phenomenon. Tuscon, Ariz.: UFO Photo Archives, 1983. Call No.: 629.4 St45u.
Stillings, Dennis, ed. "Cyberbiological Studies of the Imaginal Component in the UFO Contact Experience." Archaeus. Volume 5, 1989. [2 copies]
Story, Ronald D. UFOs and the Limits of Science. New York: William Morrow and Company, 1981.
Story, Ronald D. UFOs and the Limits of Science. New York: Morrow, 1981. Call No.: 629.4 St7u.
Strieber, Whitley. Breakthrough: The Next Step. New York: Harper Collins, 1995.
Strieber, Whitley. Communion. New York: Beech Tree Books, 1987.
Strieber, Whitley. Confirmation: The Hard Evidence of Aliens Among Us. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1998.
Strieber, Whitley. Transformation: the Breakthrough. New York: William Morrow, 1988. Call No.: 629.4 St8t.
Sturrock, Peter A. Report on a Survey of the Membership of the American Astronomical Society Concerning the UFO Problem. Stanford: Stanford University Institute for Plasma Research, 1977. Call No.: 629.4 St9r.
Sutherly, Curt. Strange Encounters: UFOs, Aliens & Monsters Among Us. St. Paul, MN: Llewellyn Publications, 1996.
Tambling, Richard. Flying Saucers: Where do they Come From? London: Scripts PTY LTD, 1967.
Terakado K[aziu ?]. The End of UFO Mythology. [work in Japanese]
Terakado K[aziu ?]. The Ruin of UFO Mythology. [work in Japanese]
Tirman, John ed. Empty Promise: The Growing Case against Star Wars. Boston: Beacon Press, 1986.
Title in Japanese.
Turner, Karla. Into the Fringe: A True Story of Alien Abduction. New York: Berkley Books, 1992.
UFO Encounters. Racine, WI: Western Publishing Co., 1978. Call No.: 629.4 Un4.
UFO: Sense and Nonsense of UFO Reports from Japanese Medias. [work in Japanese]
UFO; Magazyn Ufologiczny. Bialystok?, n.d. Call No.: 629.4 Pam. no.24.
Universal Hierarchy. A Pictorial Tour of Unarius. El Cajon, CA: Unarius Educational Foundation, 1982. Call No.: 629.4 Un4p.
Vallee, Jacques. Challenge to Science; the UFO Enigma. Chicago: Regnery, 1966. Call No.: 629.4 V24c.
Vallee, Jacques. Anatomy of a Phenomenon: the Detailed and Unbiased Report of UFOs. New York: Ace Books, 1965. Call No.: 629.4 V24a.
Vallee, Jacques. The Conspiracy Theory: Is Smersh Behind it All? Brookline, MA, 1979. Call No.: 629.4 Pam. no.23.
Vallee, Jacques. The Invisible College: What a Group of Scientists has Discovered about UFO Influences on the Human Race. New York: Dutton, 1975. Call No.: 629.4 V24i.k.
Vesco, Renato. Intercept--But Don't Shoot; the True Story of the Flying Saucers. New York, Grove Press, 1971. Call No.: 629.4 V63i.p.
Vorilhon, Claude. Let's Welcome Our Fathers from Space: They Created Humanity in Their Laboratories. Tokyo: AOM Corp., 1989. Call No.: 629.4 V91L.
Vorilhon, Claude. The Message Given to Me by Extra-terrestrials / The Extra-terrestrials Took Me to Their Planet. Tokyo: AOM Corp., 1986. Call No.: 629.4 V91m.
Walton, Travis. The Walton Experience. New York: Berkley Pub. Corp., 1978. Call No.: 629.4 W17w.
Weaver, Richard L. and James McAndrew. The Roswell Report: Fact versus Fiction in the New Mexico Desert. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1995.
Willcox, P. J. The UFO Question Roslyn Heights, N. Y.: Libra Publishers, 1976. Call No.: 629.4 W66u.
Winer, Richard. The Devil's Triangle. New York: Bantam Books, 1974. Call No.: 629.4 W72d.
Young, Mort. UFO: Top Secret. New York: Essandress Special Editions, 1967. Call No.: 629.4 Y8u.
Zinsstag, Lou. George Adamski -- The Untold Story: The Latest and Most Complete Evidence on the First Man to Claim that Extraterrestrials Live Among Us. Beckenham, Kent: Centi Publications, 1983. Call No.: 629.4 Z6g.
Bibliography
Klass, Philip J., UFOs--Identified. (New York: Random House, 1968). Call no.: 629.4 K66u
Klass, Philip J., Secret Sentries in Space (New York: Random House, 1971).
Klass, Philip J., UFOs Explained. (New York: Random House, 1974). Call no.: 629.4 K66uf
Klass, Philip J., UFOs: the Public Deceived. (Buffalo, N.Y.: Prometheus Books, 1983). Call no.: 629.4 K66ufo
Klass, Philip J., SDI--the Technical Challenge. (United States: McGraw-Hill Aerospace & Defense Group, 1986). [Interviewer: Philip J. Klass].
Klass, Philip J., UFO-Abductions: A Dangerous Game. (Buffalo, N.Y.: Prometheus Books, 1988).
Klass, Philip J., Bringing UFOs Down to Earth. (Amherst, N.Y.: Prometheus Books, 1997).
Klass, Philip J., The Real Roswell Crashed-Saucer Coverup. (Amherst, N.Y.: Prometheus Books, 1997).
Related Archival Materials note
The APS houses three collections with material relevant to UFO investigations:
In the Edward U. Condon Papers (Mss. B C752), "Series V. UFO Materials" contains documents related to Condon's position at the University of Colorado from 1966 to 1968 as head of the project "the Scientific Study of Unidentified Flying Objects," undertaken by the Air Force Office of Scientific Research to investigate claims of Unidentified Flying Objects.
The Donald Howard Menzel Papers concerning UFOs (Mss. 629.4 M52) includes correspondence, articles, newsclippings, photographs, and recordings, concerning Menzel's documentation of UFOs as natural phenomena explainable in scientific terms. One can find material on the National Investigation Committee on Aerial Phenomena, Project Blue Book, the Velikovsky controversy, and a card file of meteor activity, 1946-1961.
Ivan Terence Sanderson Papers (Mss. B Sa3) reflect his interest in animals, jungles, and natural history. Late in life, Sanderson's interest turned to UFO's and he was the director of the Society for the Investigation of the Unexplained.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Klass Papers were donated by Philip J. Klass in 1988. Additions to the collection have been made annually.
Scope and Contents note
The Collection of Philip J. Klass, an electrical engineer and UFO investigator, consist of 36 linear feet of materials documenting his writing and investigations of UFO sightings. Klass used his training as an engineer and technical writer in order to find a credible prosaic explanation for UFO sightings. Producing work on a scholarly level, Klass became one of the leading UFO skeptics along with Edward Uhler Condon and Donald Howard Menzel (whose papers are also at the APS). Klass was also instrumental in founding the Committee for the Scientific Investigation of Claims of the Paranormal (CSICOP), serving on the Executive Council and chairing the UFO subcommittee.
The collection is an ideal source for researchers investigating UFOs from a debunker's perspective, and his interaction with both the pro and con UFOlogy community. In addition, Klass' collection is valuable for the study of UFOlogy in popular culture through newspaper clippings and correspondence with the general public interested in UFOs, who openly expressed their opinions of his publications and public appearances. For historians of science and technology, the SDI material is an ideal source of material that documents the rise and decline of missile defense technology in the realms of public opinion, government policy, and technology. It contains newspaper and magazine clippings, government reports, and organizational material. It should be noted that the Klass Collection documents neither his work as an electrical engineer at GE, nor his career as an editor at AWST. The collection also lacks any documentation of Klass' personal life.
The collection is divided into eight series, and centers on Klass' UFO investigation material. Contained within the collection are correspondence, case files, subject files, material from conferences, periodicals related to UFOs, and audiovisual material.
Series I Correspondence, 1966-1992 4 boxes; 2 linear feet
Series II Case Files, 1948-1993 11 boxes; 5.5 linear feet
Series III Subject Files, 1950-1996 10 boxes; 5 linear feet
Series IV SDI Material, 1957-1991 9 boxes; 4.5 linear feet
Series V Conferences, 1968-1992 1 boxes; 0.5 linear feet
Series VI Periodicals, 1967-2000 22 boxes; 11 linear feet
Series VII A/V, 1980-1998 10 boxes; 5 linear feet
Series VIII Annotated Publications, 1975-1998 2 boxes; 1 linear feet
Biographical/Historical note
Philip J. Klass was born in Des Moines, Iowa on November 8, 1919 to Raymond and Ann Klass, and was raised along with his younger sister in Cedar Rapids. Attending Iowa State University, Klass graduated in 1941 with his bachelors of science in electrical engineering and went to work that same year as an engineer at General Electric's facility in Schenectady, NY.
In 1952 Klass became a technical journalist for Aviation Week & Space Technology (AWST) magazine, one of the leading publications for the aerospace industry. He remained with the magazine for 34 years, eventually becoming senior avionics editor. Taking semi-retirement in June 1, 1986, he continued on as a contributing editor working from home. During his time with the magazine, Klass kept a workaholic schedule putting in over forty-plus hours a week researching and writing articles. He wrote some of the first articles on inertial guidance technology, infrared missile guidance and detection, and the development of microelectronics. As a result of his work at AWST, he earned the distinction of being only one of two journalists to be named a fellow of the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE). He received awards from the Aviation/Space Writers Association in 1972, 1974, 1975, 1977, and 1986; and the Lauren D. Lyman Award in 1989 for his distinguished career. From the Royal Aeronautical Society (London) Klass received the Boeing Decade of Excellence Award for lifetime achievement in 1989.
In addition to his distinguished career as an aerospace journalist, Klass developed a career investigating UFO sightings. Klass began investigating UFOs in 1966 after participating in a panel discussion for the IEEE. Unfamiliar with the subject, he read John G. Fuller's Incident at Exeter: the Story of Unidentified Flying Objects Over America Today (New York: Putnam, 1966), which contained reports of glowing fireballs near high-tension power lines, and began looking at the possibility that UFOs could be nothing more then freak atmospheric electrical phenomenon such as ball lighting. When he entered the field of UFO investigation he held the premise that people were honestly reporting what they believed they saw. He soon learned that people sometimes held ulterior motives when reporting UFO sightings. His first investigation in 1966 of a sighting two years earlier near Socorro, NM showed that the report was merely a hoax in an attempt to bring tourism to the economically depressed town.